<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands monarch, or, A conviction and refutation by the common law, of those false principles and insinuating flatteries of Albericus delivered by way of disputation, and after published, and dedicated to our dread soveraigne King James, in which he laboureth to prove by the civill law, our prince to be an absolute monarch and to have a free and arbitrary power over the lives and estates of his people : together with a generall confutation (and that grounded upon certaine principles taken by some of their owne profession) of all absolute monarchy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10980</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13011413</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13011413</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96490</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96490)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 737:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands monarch, or, A conviction and refutation by the common law, of those false principles and insinuating flatteries of Albericus delivered by way of disputation, and after published, and dedicated to our dread soveraigne King James, in which he laboureth to prove by the civill law, our prince to be an absolute monarch and to have a free and arbitrary power over the lives and estates of his people : together with a generall confutation (and that grounded upon certaine principles taken by some of their owne profession) of all absolute monarchy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Paine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Regales disputationes tres" is the title of the book discussed. Cf. p. [3].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gentili, Alberico, 1552-1608. --  Regales disputationes tres.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96490:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96490:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS MONARCH, OR A CONVICTION AND refutation by the Common law, of thoſe falſe Principles and inſinuating flatteries of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi> delivered by way of Diſputation, and after pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and dedicated to our dread Soveraigne King JAMES, in which he laboureth to prove by the Civill Law, our Prince to be an abſolute Monarch; and to have a free and Arbitrary power over the lives and Eſtates of his people.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH A GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall confutation (and that grounded vpon certaine Principles taken by ſome of their owne profeſſion) of all abſolute <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Paine, Anno Dom.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96490:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THis worke (after ſo much labour and expence of time by others in the like ſubiect) may now be thought vaine and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſcarce deſerving the vacant houres of a mans time; much leſſe thoſe oppertunities, which neceſſary occaſions and imployments call for. But <hi>Reader</hi> let not this make you vilipend or undervalue his endeavour; who doth here preſent you, with ſuch a peece of <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> that hapily you never read, nor heard off; and that is <hi>Alberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> publiſhed in latine, the great propugnor of our King to be an abſolute Monarch; which he would mainetaine too by the Civell Law; and who but our good King <hi>JAMES</hi> muſt be made the Patron of theſe abſurde Principles. Give me but your patience, I will not acomagere, tread in others ſteps, the <hi>Author</hi> hath lead me into a large field of novelty; where if you pleaſe to ſolace your ſelfe but a while; you ſhall finde it more apt to informe your iudgement, then confirme your memory; which if made good unto you, let him have your favourable cenſure, who ever was, and will be a faithfull ſervant to his Country.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96490:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS <hi>MONARCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving by accident met with a Book full of the fallacies of theſe times, and yet dedicated to our late Soveraigne King <hi>Iames;</hi> and for ought I can be informed paſſed over in ſilence without the leaſt reproofe. I thought it my duty out of that faith and loyaltie that I owe to my King and Countrey to publiſh its prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to the world, and by the way as I goe to give a particular anſwer to every one of them.</p>
            <p>The Authors name is <hi>Albericus;</hi> what Country man I know not, but his name as alſo his principles ſeeme to ſpeake him a ſtranger by birth, and a Civilian by his profeſſion.</p>
            <p>His Book is intituled, <hi>Three Regall diſputations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Regales Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putationes tres.</note> And the firſt is; <hi>Of the abſolute power of the King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Depoteſtate Regis abſolutae</note> And this is the taske that I have at this time impoſed upon my ſelfe, to debate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the abſurditie of this principle; being a Tenet utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant and abſolutely deſtructive to the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and the Liberties of the Subject.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that the greateſt part of the unhappie he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall principles of this Booke, are at this day defended by force of Armes, by ſuch as would be called Royaliſts, or if you will the Kings friends; while in the meane time they ſell their Birthright and inheritance for a poore meſſe of Pottage; and become Actors in this ſad Tragedie of the ruine of their King and Countrey. But to begin with the Author, who in the very firſt poſition of his Booke, were it Orthodox in this Kingdom, would quite confound all our Lawes and Liberties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which pleaſeth the Prince</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath the force of a Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi placvit Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis habet vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorem pag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> I this is that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> your Prelaticall flatterers &amp; Paraſiticall Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers perſwade his Majeſty; and this peece of poyſon they have ſuckt out of ſuch unworthy underminers of their own Liberty, as my Author is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96490:3"/>
            <p>And this he ſaies, to be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 5.</note>
               <hi>a regall Law brought in by his Empire, for that the people have conferred upon him all their rule and power.</hi> That is, the people have given power to their Prince to bee a Tyrant, and tread them under feet at liberty, a principle ſo void of reaſon, that it carries not the leaſt colour or probabality with it; but of this hereafter.</p>
            <p>But this poſition <hi>Quod Principi placuit, &amp;c.</hi> That which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Prince hath the force of a Law. He ſaith, <hi>is to to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Romane Emperour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>for his excellency above others;</hi> as alſo for other reaſons that he renders. If this bee ſo <hi>Albericus,</hi> what have we that are Engliſh Subjects &amp; live under a Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Law to doe with that? or why diddeſt thou dedicate this unſound and unwarrantable peece of flattery to our King? couldeſt thou imagine ſo learned and ſo wiſe a Prince would be wrought upon to ſubvert the Lawes, and enſlave his Subjects: who can make as good a Title by the Law to their liberty as the King to his Crowne? But <hi>Albericus</hi> well knew that the beſt Princes might be corrupted; and that ambition may cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate the Crowne, as well as the Peaſant. I even in thoſe dayes, our Liberties were invaded by the infuſion of ſuch falſe Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes as theſe are; And to this houre we groane under that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie burthen; my little finger ſhall bee heavier then my Fathers Loynes.</p>
            <p>And though we live under a Municipall Law, which utterly denies and condemnes theſe flattering poſitions of the Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; as abſolutely deſtructive to that freedom wee were borne under; yet my Author doth affirme that all interpeters (that is of the Civill Law) without any difficulty do attribute this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to all ſupreame Princes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now hence he raiſes a queſtion who thoſe ſupreame Princes are?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 7, 8, 9.</note> And the ſome of his definition of the ſupreame Princes may be reduced ſhortly to this; <hi>They are ſupreame Princes, who neither have, nor acknowledge any one above them but God, and to him onely are bound to render an account; who are free from all Law, whoſe willis a ſufficien treaſon; &amp; whoſe reaſon is as an abſolute law.</hi> And he ſaies <hi>this is no barbarous Law, but the Romane Law.</hi> If ſo <hi>Albericus,</hi> why doe ſuch Sycophants vent their poyſon here in England. Sir, God be thanked wee have a Law of our owne, whoſe fundamentalls crye downe this definition as paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to ſence and reaſon; whoſe light is ſo great, that it neede not borrow of others to adde to its perfection.</p>
            <p>But here wee may ſee that the ſame Doctrine is preached to
<pb facs="tcp:96490:3"/>our King at this day; that was to his predeceſſor; what elſe meant the long diſcountinance of Parliaments, the onely aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we have of the continuance of our Lawes and Liberties? I and what meanes the taking up of Armes too againſt them? But yet to come nearer to this definition of the Civilians of an abſolute Prince, what meanes that frequent expreſſion of His Majeſtie in His Declarations, that he is reſponſible to God alone for his actions? I am certaine this is <hi>Lex Romana,</hi> the Romane Law.</p>
            <p>But when hee had ſhewne what is not this ſupreame power, and who are not theſe ſupreame Princes, (he ſaith,) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 10.</note>
               <hi>That our King is amongst the other Kings, that is, the ſupreame Princes, who are free from the Law, which is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of an abſolute power and this is not ſubject either to the rules of neceſſity, or publique Law.</hi> Then he ſaies that <hi>there is poteſtas extraordinaria &amp; libera, an extraordinary and free power, which</hi> he ſaies, <hi>in England wee doe ſignifie by the name Regiae Praerogativae, of the Royall Prerogative.</hi> And further he ſayes, <hi>That the interpreters of their Law doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly write that there is a double power in a Prince; the one ordinary bound by the Law; the other extraordinary, free from the Law; and hee ſaies, that they define that to be the abſolute power by which hee may take away another mans right, though it be great, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is this that extraordinary power which we by the Law of England call the Royall Prerogative? I wonder at the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and the ignorance of the Author, that ſhould publiſh a thing ſo abſolutely contrary to the knowne Lawes of the Realme: but I will refute him by our Law, and not by ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though he deſerves no better.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that our King (according to their own definition) is not one of theſe ſupreame Princes, or abſolute Monarches, nothing more pregnant or plainely demonſtrable in our Law: For hee is under the Law, and ſo ſaies <hi>Bracton</hi> and <hi>Fleta,</hi> two of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienteſt Law Bookes in ſeverall places commonly knowne; ſo that I neede not to cite them. But <hi>Bracton</hi> goes further,<note place="margin">Bracton de ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirendo rerum Domino. fol. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> that not onely <hi>habet legem ſuperiorem;</hi> the Law is above him, but alſo <hi>curiam ſuam viz. Comites, Barones, &amp;c.</hi> (which can bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of no other then the Parliament,) that that likewiſe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him: why then if both Law &amp; Parliament be above him, he can be no abſolute Monarch according to themſelves. But further by the Lawes and conſtitutions of this Kingdome, the Legiſlative power doth not reſide in the King alone (for he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:96490:4"/>create a Law, or deſtroy, or diſanull any Law, by his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or Proclamation) but in the three eſtates joyntly together aſſembled in one body in Parliament; and therefore to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our Prince to be an obſolute Monarch is utterly to oppoſe and overthrow the fundamentalls of our Lawe. But how ſatte this is laboured at this day, I leave it to the conſciences of al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men to judge; for if the King might have power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continue Parliaments as long as he pleaſeth; or being called, to have a negative Voyce to all their reaſonable demands, will not this bee a compendious way to bring all the Legiſlative power into his owne hands? But then he ſais, that <hi>by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary or abſolute power,</hi> (which he would have our Prince to have) <hi>He may take away any mans right, be it never ſo great.</hi> For he ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 13.</note> That <hi>the Prince by his Empire poſſeſſes all things, that he hath an imperiall and univerſall dominion, though the particular and private be in the proprietor.</hi> Which in plainer Engliſh, is to tell you, that the King hath an intereſt and power over every mans particular property, which is as abſolutely falſe, as can be imagined; and ſtands as much in oppoſition to our Law, as one contrary can to another, for what then would become of our Petition of Right? Or how could we ſay that we had right to any thing, when the King at his owne pleaſure, might diſpoſſeſſe us of all? this were a ready way to inſlave us, and to make us hould by that baſe tenure of Villeinage. I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but that the Common wealth hath an intereſt paramount the property of every private man; but this is not left to the ſole diſpoſition of our Prince, but the Parliament, who may diſpoſe of the generall intereſt, for the good of the Common wealth, and in ſuch caſe we our ſelves are the free diſpenſers of our owne; for tis not more their power, then our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents that binds us. But thankes be to God, that every man by our Law, (let Court Paraſites ſay what they will) hath as abſolute a right in that hee enjoyes, as his Prince claimes in his Crowne, nay I may be bold to affirme (without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the royall intereſt) that he hath a greater: for that the King is ſeiſed or poſſeſſed in the right of his Crowne onely; the people in their owne right. What one principle more aumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke in our law then this; that the King cannot take away any mans property without his owne conſent; and how is this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be purchaſed? why no otherwiſe then by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with whom the generall property (which is above eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans particular intereſt) is intruſted. And therefore thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:96490:4"/>that will have the King to be an abſolute Monarch over his people, muſt inſtruct him how to repeale <hi>Magna charta,</hi> and all the other Lawes made in confirmation of it, and the Subjects liberty, before they can court them into ſlavery.</p>
            <p>But here it will be objected, that the lawes of this Realme doe avow and maintaine our King to be an abſolute Monarch; very juſt, and with this difference wee ſhall allow him to be ſo; that is, as to all forraine power, authority, or juriſdiction what ſoever, he is an obſolute Emperor within theſe his dominions: in plainer language he is no dependent or tributary Prince: but is (as he is acknowledged to be by the ſtatute of 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 12,) <hi>Furniſhed with plenary, whole, and intire power, preeminence, authority, prerogative and juriſdistion, &amp;c.</hi> So that no forraine Prince or Potentate whatſoever, can challenge or excerciſe the leaſt authority in theſe Kingdomes; but this doth no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our Prince to be an abſolute Monarch in the excerciſe of his juriſdiction over his people. Tis true that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſayes our King is an abſolute King: but how? not over his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and that is cleared by the caſe that he puts, which is this. <hi>Artold</hi> King of <hi>Manne</hi> ſued to King <hi>H.</hi> 3. to come into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c. upon which my Lord Coke obſerves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>fo.</hi> 21.</note> that ſeeing that <hi>Artold</hi> King of <hi>Manne,</hi> ſued for a licence in this caſe to our King, it proveth him an abſolute King, which is evident, as to any forraine power or authority whatſoever, but not to his own Subjects. For as to them, he hath but a qualified, limitted power, confined to the rules of law, &amp; the cuſtoms of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Theſe things pondered on, I ſtand amazed at thy bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, confidence <hi>Albericus,</hi> that durſt affirme our King to be an abſolute Monarch, and canſt prove it no better, then by the daubing principles of the Civill Law: what elſe is this but to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue a caſe at Common Law, upon the notions and grounds of the Civil; which were an abſurdity next to madneſſe. But I ſtand moſt aſtoniſhed, when I conſider that our Prince muſt be made the Patron of ſuch dangerous abſurde principles. This is that that hath ſo much advanced Prerogative, and depreſſed Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And theſe times are become the ſad effect and conſequence of ſuch flattering falſities.</p>
            <p>But now having clearely evidenced it that our King is no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Monarch and ſo hath no power over the lives, liberties, or eſtates of his Subjects, more then the law alloweth. You ſhall now heare ſeverall reaſons given in my Author totally to oppoſe this opinion of abſolute Monarchy, which with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb facs="tcp:96490:5"/>of the curteous Reader, are no way anſwered by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra-diſputant, and for my part, I thinke that abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is much like Sir <hi>Tho. Mores Eutopiae,</hi> no where to be found.</p>
            <p>And firſt you ſhall heare how one of their owne inveighes againſt this opinion. Sayes he, <hi>Thoſe things that are done by this clauſe of ſupreame power, not by way of iuſtice; but becauſe it ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Prince, and no man could ſay to him Cur it a facis? why doe you ſo? It is no other then violence; which</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>by a more honeſt title is called the ſupreame power.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt acknowledge it ever was, and ſhall be my opinion, that though Princes are ſtiled Gods here on earth, yet their power is ſo qualified, that they ought not to live according to their own will, but the rule of reaſon and religion; and if they paſſe theſe, let flatterers qualifie their actions as they can, more ſound and honeſt judgements wil ſay, that they are but violence &amp; tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Againe ſaies the ſame Author,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Your great Governors &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors lay ſnares every where in the way</hi> (that is to catch and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap their Prince) <hi>Your Divines they erre</hi> (and make their Prince doe the like) <hi>And your Lawyers they faune and flatter; and all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their Prince that all things are lawfull for him, and that be hath free and abſolute power to doe what he liſt.</hi> And is not this the very dialect of theſe times? Hath not <hi>Briſtow, Digby</hi> and <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington</hi> and ſuch like perfideous Counſellors, ſeduced his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie from his Parliament, and perſwaded him that it is lawfull for him to take up Armes againſt them, and to ſtate himſelfe (if poſſibly he may) in an abſolute Monarchy? Doe not your Divines preach prerogative, in ſtead of Divinity, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence detrude the Subjects liberty? And now I could wiſh that our great Lawyers could puill their necks out of the halter, the coller I ſhould ſay. But it is ſad newes, that the Ship-mony is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine revived. The King muſt be ſole Judge, (I and that in his owne caſe too) when the Kingdome is indangered, and ſo by this ſlight, might dive into his Subjects purſes, when, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he himſelfe pleaſed. Now pray what doth the negative voyce in Parliament (ſo ſtiffely defended by our Lawyres of <hi>Oxford</hi>) differ from this, if the King ſhal be ſole Judge of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity or conveniency of any Lawes preſented unto him by his people? doe but ſupport this ground of the Kings being Judge in his owne caſe, down goes all the fundamentalls of our Lawe preſently. No way more exact or abſolute to bring in <hi>Quod Principi placet, &amp;c.</hi> and to obtrude the liberty of the Subject. But that you may ſee how farre this abſolute power is laboured
<pb facs="tcp:96490:5"/>for at this day; they have derived this very principle, from this unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Law of liberty, as I ſhall make it appeare hereafter. But now let us reaſon the point, and heare what is objected againſt this abſolute power of Princes.</p>
            <p>Sais one <hi>all Dominion or Soveraignetie is for the publique profit of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or Subiects, not of thoſe that raigne or rule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16.</note> To this <hi>Albericus</hi> ſaies, <hi>that it is a falſe foundation in thoſe principalities or dominions that are got by force; and not totally true in thoſe who are induced or brought in by the people;</hi> For he ſaies, that <hi>due honour was given to the vertues of thoſe Princes that were choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my part I never read or heard <hi>Albericus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16.</note> that a Prince who hath gained a Kingdome by Conqueſt, is diſobliged from the rule of Reaſon; and Religion. The Scripture doth no where warrant (that I know of) any Prince whatſoever to be a Tyrant, which I am ſure he muſt needs bee, that ſeekes his owne, not his peoples good. This is but juſt, that due honour ſhould be given to the vertues of thoſe Princes that are elected; but ſuch as reverence them, ſo far, as to attribute an abſoluteneſſe of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto them, and give them liberty to do what they liſt; doe diſhonour God, in aſcribing that power that was never given; &amp; debaſe their Prince, by making him to degenerate from true Soveraignety into Tyranny.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> by way of Diriſion faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>that wee make our Princes like Phyſitians, whoſe rule or power is for the ſake of thoſe only, who are their Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents.</hi> My opinion is, that Princes cannot be more properly compared or aſſimulated, then unto Phyſitians; the one is the Phyſitian for the body naturall, the other for the body politique. A Prince ought to purge out all ill humours; that is, ill members out of the Common wealth; hee ought to tender the lives and happineſſe of his people, as much as a Phyſitian the life and good of his Patient. Nay, as a Phyſitian ought to have an eye more to the good and ſafety of his Patient, then his owne benefit, ſo ought this great Phyſition of the Common wealth. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces happineſſe is involved in the good of his people, &amp; therefore they doe but teach him how to ruine himſelf, that inſtruct him to undoe his people</p>
            <p>But <hi>Albericus</hi> reaſons further, by way of admittance, what ſais he <hi>if all Dominion or Power were ordained for the onely benefit of Subiects? Ergo ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudo poteſtatis non eſt, is there not therefore a plenitude of power?</hi> Sir, wee doe not denie but that Princes have full power and authority to governe their people; but we doe, and ſhall ever deny, that they have an abſolute power to Tyrannize over them.</p>
            <p>But he ſaies further, that <hi>it is for the benefit and profit of Subiects' that a Prince ſhould have this power.</hi> I marry Sir, witneſſe the great utility,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16.</note> that accrues to the Subject at this day, by the exerciſe of the like power. That their lives and eſtates ſhould be at the ſole will, beck, and command of their Soveraigne; this is for the benefit of the Subject. Pray give me
<pb facs="tcp:96490:6"/>leave to put you a plaine caſe in Law. <hi>A.</hi> gives land to <hi>B.</hi> in truſt, and for the onely uſe of <hi>C. B.</hi> breakes the truſt, and diſpoſes of the Land at his owne pleaſure; reſolve me this queſtion; is not this for the benefit of <hi>C?</hi> Such, and only ſuch benefit accrues to the Subject, by giving of an abſolute power to the Prince. But ſo much for this argument.</p>
            <p>The next poſition that is diſcuſſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 17.</note> is, that <hi>abſoluteneſſe of power is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in God, and is not communicable to any other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this <hi>Albericus</hi> anſwers that <hi>this doth not make the Prince equall to God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>for nevertheleſſe he is under God, and is bound by the Lawes of God: God</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>is ſimply abſolute not bound to any Law; but the Prince onely abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute to ſome reſpects: for though he be above the Civill Law, yet he is under the Law of God, of Nature, and of Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will allow this abſolute power that you ſpeake of, if you cane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us out of holy Writ (to which Princes as well as people, owe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection) that ever ſuch power was communicated to any juſt Prince that he might diſpoſe of the lives, and eſtates, of his Subjects at his owne will and pleaſure; what is this but Tyrranny? and if God (who only hath abſolute power over his people) did ſometimes in his wrath for the ſinnes of his people, put a Tyrannicall King over them, yet this is no warrant for others to be ſo. God who is the only proprietor and free diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſer of all things; and giveth what he pleaſeth, and to whom and when he pleaſeth what he out of his bounty doth beſtow upon his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſervant; he doth inveſt him in as pure and abſolute a right, as he doth the greateſt Prince in his Monarchy, and therefore it lies not in the power of his Prince to diſpoſſeſſe him of it.</p>
            <p>We have a moſt exact, and perfect diſcription of a Tyrant in the word. of God. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. where, when the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not contented with that Governement, that God had appointed over them, asked a King of <hi>Samuell;</hi> God in his anger, and as a judgement upon the people for their ſin, gave them a King to rule over them, but ſuch a one, who (according to the diſcription of <hi>Samuell</hi>) would make his will his Law; for ſaies <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell</hi> to the people, <hi>This will be the manner of the King that ſhall reigne over you, he will take your ſonnes and appoint them for himſelfe, for his Charets, &amp;c. And he will appoint him Captaines over thouſands, &amp;c. And he will take your daughters to be confectioners, &amp;c. And hee will take your fields and your vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards and give them to his ſervants. And he will take your ſervants and cattle and put them to worke, &amp;c.</hi> Here you have a compleate delineation of a Tyrant. For marke, <hi>Samuell</hi> tells the people what he will doe, not what he ought to doe; thus, and thus he will doe ſaith he; and he will render no better reaſon for what he doth, <hi>ſtat pro ratione voluntas,</hi> his will is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſufficient to deprive you of your ſubſtance, and to inſlave you and your poſtetity for ever. This was the judgement of God, and therefore not to be drawne in example, or made a preſident for others. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:96490:6"/>let every unjuſt Prince take heede that (whileſt hee is made the Rod and ſcourge of God for his peoples ſinnes) hee himſelfe be not at the laſt throwne into the fire.</p>
            <p>But now you ſhall heare the duty of a good Prince ſet forth in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17 <hi>He ſhall not multiply horſes to himſelfe, &amp;c. Neither ſhall he multiply wives, nor ſilver and gold. He ſhall write him a coppie of this Law in a Booke, &amp;c. And it ſhall be with him, and hee ſhall reade therein all the dayes of his life, that hee may learne to feare the Lord his God, to keepe all the words of this Law, and theſe ſtatutes to doe them.</hi> Now marke what followes all, <hi>That his heart be not lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up above his brethren, &amp;c.</hi> For my part I do not find here that the Kings will is a Law, or that he hath power to open, &amp; ſhut the purſes of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at his pleaſure. A juſt Prince muſt not multiply ſilver &amp; gold; why then doubtleſſe he muſt not doe it upon the ruines of his Subjects. Hee muſt keepe this law; and I am ſure this Law doth not make him law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, or juſtifie Tyranny. And laſtly his heart muſt not bee lifted up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his brethren, that is, he muſt not ſo exalt his owne power, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and deſtroy his people.</p>
            <p>Another Argument is this, that <hi>the people did tranſferre this power to the King, that by it they might be more commodiouſly governed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>but this is not that ſupreame power, ſic volo, ſic jubeo,</hi> but an ordinary power directed by law.</p>
            <p>To this <hi>Albericus</hi> anſwers, with his diſtinction before taken, that <hi>there is an ordinary and an extraordinary power in the Prince;</hi> and he ſaies, that <hi>the people ſometimes by this extraordinary power</hi> (which is the ſupreame and abſolute power) <hi>may be governed more commodiouſly,</hi> for he ſaies, <hi>That peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of indomitable and rigid ſpirits are better governed by this extraordinary, then an ordinary power, and thoſe Subjects are to be governed by an Iron Rod, that will not yeeld to the ferula.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly <hi>Albericus</hi> when he wrote this booke, thought he had been tutering of children. I confeſſe that I have often read and heard that the government by Monarchy, is much to be preferred and ſet before <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy, Democracy,</hi> or <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi>|; but I never heard that tyranny might be more apt &amp; commodious then a juſt and lawfull governement; neither did I ever read of any people of ſo ſavedge and barbarous a nature, who would not rather ſtoope to a juſt and legall then an unjuſt and tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dominion. No queſtion it is moſt commodious both for King and people, that the one ſhould have a certain poſitive rule by which he might governe; and the other by which he might obey. And that Prince who governs his people by the rule of juſtice, ſhall find more faithfull and loyall Subjects, then he that ſwayes them by the Scepter of an extraordinary and tyrannicall power.</p>
            <p>But heare what <hi>Albericus</hi> doth determin to be tyranny. That ſayes he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 25.</note>
               <hi>is tyrannous, which in a tyrant is wonted and ordinary; in aiuſt Prince extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb facs="tcp:96490:7"/>and caſuall. To take away famous and excellent men, to expell or drive away thoſe that are wiſe, to exterminate ſtudies, to have and countenance ſuch about him as are envious, private calumniators and accuſers of others, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low &amp; delight in bloody warres, theſe &amp; others of that kind, he ſaies to be tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous.</hi> How <hi>Albericus</hi> are theſe tyrannous? I thought the ſupreame pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had beene unlimitted, why ſo it is: for he ſaies, that even theſe very actions, which imediatly before he ſtyles tyrannous, <hi>Poſſunt aliquandoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam eſſe juſta, may ſometimes be juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May tyrannous actions be juſt? what a diametricall contradiction is this? he may as well call darkeneſſe, light, or light darkeneſſe, good, evill, or evill, good. In vaine doth he labour to make this good, by ſtrange and tyrannous actions, (as he would have them) which are done by Princes for the good of the common wealth, neither is this <hi>malum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſariun,</hi> a neceſſary evill, as he calls it, for whatſoever is ſimply tyranous, cannot be ſaid to be juſt, and whatſoever is done (and in truth is ſo) for the common good cannot beare the infamous ſcandall of tyrannous. But this ſaying of <hi>Albericus</hi> ſavours more of <hi>Machavilians Politiques,</hi> then of juſt and legall governement,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>That this abſolute power of which he treats, and which be confeſſes to be at will; muſt be taken ta the will of a good man.</hi> A very good diſtinction; why then belike a prince that is an unjuſt and corrupt man, cannot uſe this ſupreame and arbitrary power. O yes; for immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>he doth affirme, the Prince to be this good man;</hi> As if it were an abſolute and uncontrollable conſequence, that every Prince muſt be a good man, Whereas the Scripture holds out cleare teſtimony of the wickedneſſe &amp; corruption of Princes. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45.9. <hi>Job</hi> 34.30. <hi>Amos</hi> 4.1. And ſuch was the tyranny of the Princes of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that in <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.3. they are called roaring Lyons. Obſerve but his way of reaſoning, Every Prince that is a good man hath this arbytrary power: But every Prince is a good man Therefore every Prince hath this arbitrary power. The falſeſt <hi>Sillogiſme,</hi> and the moſt pure implicite contradiction that ever was. For the Major propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, clearely implies that every Prince is not good, the Minor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes every one to be good. But here you may ſee the ſenceleſſe dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of theſe men; who are reſolved to put a good gloſſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fouleſt actions; and rather then their Prince ſhall not be, what they would have him, they will moſt boldly affirme to be that which he is not. But woe be to you that call good evill, or evill good. I ſhall ſay no more but this. Happy <hi>England</hi> were greatneſſe and goodneſſe, inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concomitants.</p>
            <p>But he ſteps a little neater to us, and ſaies <hi>Though the Prince hath a pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag.</note> 
               <hi>yet the ought to uſe this iuſtly; otherwiſe it will be a plenitude of ſtormes and tempeſts.</hi> And he further ſates: <hi>That this clauſe of the fullneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:96490:7"/>power, is under ſtood of a good and laudable power &amp; not a power to ill or iniury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſtrange and unparallel'd contradictions are theſe? How can this ſtand with the former poſitions? that the King may doe what he liſt, that his will is a ſufficient reaſon, and his reaſon a poſitive law, if the King may be ſaid to doe that, which is unjuſt, ill or injurious. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ill or injury, are not things compatible to abſolute Monarchy, give me leave a little to reaſon the caſe out of <hi>Albericus</hi> himſelfe. Thoſe that have not power to doe what they liſt, have no abſolute power. But Kings cannot doe what they liſt: Therefore Kings have no abſolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. But here the Minor prepoſition will be denied, that Kings may doe what they liſt. To this I anſwer with <hi>Albericus,</hi> that Kings cannot doe wrong or injury, therefore Kings cannot doe what they liſt. And hence the conſequence is very evident, that Kings have no abſolute power.</p>
            <p>But he doth yet approach nearer to us, in denying the opinion of ſome of their owne formerly delivered; for he ſaies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>That the Prince by this ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude or abſolutenes of power, cannot deprive his Subiects of their dominions or properties, ſine cauſa iuſta,</hi> without juſt cauſe tendered.</p>
            <p>Why now <hi>Albericus ſecundumte,</hi> according to your owne argument: if Kings cannot take away their Subjects properties, but are bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate their actions according to the rule of juſtice; How can Kings be ſaid to have an abſolute power? Why yes, you ſhall heare how, for he doth afterwards, (if what he ſaies would hold) make good whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he hath delivered: or indeed can deliver in the defence of this tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, abſolute Monarchy. For he ſaies, <hi>That of the iuſtneſſe of this cauſe, this abſolute Prince is the ſole Judge and Arbitor.</hi> Now you know upon what foundation that principle of the Shipmony was built; that the King on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to be Judge of the imminent danger then pretended. This is that which was taught by evill Councellors, one whereof (with whom the dominion of <hi>Ireland</hi> was intruſted) was wont to ſay, that he had the law lockt up in <hi>ſcrinio pectoris,</hi> in the cloſſet of his owne breſt: which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in plainer language ſpeakes clearely this, that his will was a law. But he that then thought to have advanced his Soveraigne, (&amp; by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence himſelfe) above law, hath ſence undergone his juſt demerit; and the law ſtill lives in ſpite of its enemies. But who would have thought that our grave fathers and ſage determiners, the <hi>lex loquens,</hi> or walking Libraries of our law; ſhould have beene ſo perfidious to their own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as to borrow grounds of the Civill law, to make up a judgement ſo diſtructive to the Common. And that that was ſo, give me leave to reaſon the caſe a little, I will make it evident. For firſt they themſelves ſay that to bee the only diſcrimen or true difference betwixtabſolute (if any ſuch thing there be) and quallified or limitted Monarchy. For ſay they, the firſt doth judge <hi>de cauſis,</hi> of cauſes; and the latter <hi>ex legibus,</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:96490:8"/>the lawes. So that give but the King leave to be judge in his owne caſe, you preſently mount him into abſolute monarchy: if this were law, the King might take away any mans eſtate upon juſt cauſe; I and whether it were juſt or no, he would doe it, for he himſelfe ſhould be judge of the cauſe and then it would not be difficult to determine on whoſe ſide the judgement ſhould be given. Tis an undoubted Maxime that no man can be acompetent judge in his owne caſe, and it is all one to give the King li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betty to take away his Subiects rights uniuſtly; as to ſay he cannot doe it, but upon iuſt ground, and yet to leave that to his ſole ſudgement, and determination. Might not the King in that caſe, as often as he himſelfe pleaſed, have exhauſted his Subiects treaſure upon pretence of an immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger? and if he be ſole Judge of the neceſſity, who could oppoſe it? But you ſee the abſurdity and ill conſequence of this principle, and therefore ſo I ſhall leave it.</p>
            <p>But then ſpeaking how farre the law ſhould be obligatory to the Prince,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 2.8.</note> he takes theſe diſtinctions: ſaies he, <hi>There is Lex honeſtatis, the law of honeſty; and Lex neceſſitatis, the law of neceſſity.</hi> The law of honeſty that binds the King; that is, the King in point of honeſty may if he will obſerve the law, if he will not he may make his will his law. The law of neceſſity, that bindes the Subiect, ſo that will he, nill he, he muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and give obedience to it.</p>
            <p>Others he ſaies, ſay <hi>That there is the law of honeſty, and the law of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept;</hi> and he ſaies the one doth not leſſe oblige, then the other, yet there is this difference, that the law of honeſty depends onely upon the will of the prince: what an abſurdity is this, to ſay that the one doth as ſtrongly bind as the other, and yet that the one muſt obſerve the law and the other is at his liberty, whether he will or no.</p>
            <p>Others he ſaies, ſay <hi>That there is neceſſitas rei, the neceſſity of the thing &amp; neceſſitas perſonae, the neceſſity of the perſon,</hi> ſo that though the thing may be of neceſſity to be done, (as for the purpoſe the ſetling of the <hi>Militia</hi>) yet that doth not neceſſitare the perſon of an abſolute Prince to doe it.</p>
            <p>What pure contradictions are theſe, firſt that Princes have Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame and abſolute power to do what they liſt, and yet that they ought to do nothing, but what is juſt and right. That they are above the Law, and yet by the law of honeſty they are bound to obſerve and keepe it. I thinke it is almoſt impoſſible to reconcile theſe differences, or to make <hi>Albericus</hi> agree with himſelfe. For my part, I ſhall not ſticke to defend that Princes by the law of neceſſity, are bound to ſubmit to the Law, as well as their people; For I am ſure that the divine precept doth as ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblige the greateſt Monarch, as the meaneſt begger; and that requires that juſtice be done to all men, and that every man (which exempts not Princes) ſhould doe that, which hee commands others to doe. Now it is
<pb facs="tcp:96490:8"/>but conſonant to the rule of juſtice and good government, that Princes ſhould be neceſſitated to obſerve the Law as well as their people; for if the King ſhall have power to make his will his law, what juſtice or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led governement can be exſpected. Then this beeing an act of juſtice to obſerve the Law, by that generall precept of the word of God, that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be done to all men; Princes are as ſtrongly obliged to it as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Againe, if the Divine rule requireth that every man doe that which he commandeth to be done by another; why then no Prince can excuſe himſelfe of the neceſſity of ſubjection to that Law; which he requireth ſhould be kept and obſerved by his Subjects. I am certaine it is the very letter of the Word and a principall part of juſtice, that every man ſhould doe, as he would be done by; and I am confident no Prince if hee would ſtate himſelfe in the place of his Subject, could hold it juſt or equali, that it ſhould lie in the breſt of his Soveraigne to vaſſalize him at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Now a man ought not to doe that, or to conceive it juſt to be done to another, which he would condemne as unjuſt, being done to himſelfe. I never complied with that diſtinction of ſome Divines, who ſay the Prince to be ſubject to the directive, but not to the coactive or compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive power of the law; for though they may be exempt from the penall, yet not from the coercive power; and without controverſie, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God requires, of that man may exact the juſt and due performance. And as I have ſaid, the word of God doth rather binde over Princes by the law of neceſſity, to the obſervance of the Law, then any way give them freedome from it, or power againſt it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, you ſhall heare how ſome of their own argue; <hi>frustra ſint Leges poſitae noſtro principi, niſi ſit, qui ipſum in leges cogat;</hi> that is, <hi>it is in vaine to tie our Prince to the Lawes, except there ſhould be ſomebody to compell him to the obſervation of them.</hi> And ſaies another, <hi>why are not the lawes alſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated, with which the Prince is ſaid to be bound, if it can never be, that hee may be compelled to keepe and obſerve them?</hi> Every Law carries with it a coactive neceſſity of obſervance; and as good no Law, as no power to exact the performance of the Law: But heare what a third of their owne ſayes; <hi>The Lawes are the conventions or covenants betwixt the Prince and his people, &amp; it is the nature of obligations to enforce the unwilling,</hi> &amp; the bond and obligation being mutuall, tis but juſt and equall that Kings ſhould be neceſſitated to obſerve the law as well as their people. To conclude this, give but Kings freedome from the coercive power of the Law; you make the Law as vaine and idle, as their covenants and obligations.</p>
            <p>The laſt argument that I ſhall touch, is this; that <hi>if the people were bound by their owne Lawes, ſo ſhould the Prince, if the people conferre their power upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this it is ſaid, that <hi>this power collated by the people to the Prince, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted
<pb facs="tcp:96490:9"/>of the people, of Magistrates, and of the Lawes themſelves;</hi> that is, he hath power over all theſe, then it is ſaid, <hi>can hee who hath the Lawes in his power, be in the power of the lawes? or can he that hath the power of the Lawes, be detayned by the power of the Lawes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my part <hi>Albericus</hi> I count it a flat abſurdity for any man to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that the people conferred a grater power or exemption upon their Prince, then they themſelves had, or exerciſed, for though they did tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre all the Legiſlative power to the Prince, yet it muſt be clogged with the ſame qualifications and conditions that they themſelves had it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be imagined by ſounder judgements, that people who had ſuch experience of an ample liberty, would give an abſolute power to their Prince, and thereby ſubject themſelves to the bond of ſlavery. That the people did grant to their Prince a power of making Lawes; doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him an exemption or freedome from them. Beſides as the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Governement in any ſtate are dangerous, and therefore not to be attempted without mature conſideration, ſo it hath beene alwaies the care and vigelancy of all States whatſoever upon their innovation or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Governement, to reduce themſelves to a better, not a worſe condition; and can we then conceive that the Nations upon the firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Princes, could be ſo ſtuped as to ſubmit themſelves to abſolute Monarchy, &amp; live under the lawleſs power of Tyranny? and ſo avoiding one extreame to fal into another much worſe then the former. For my ſelfe, I muſt needes acknowledge that it is a thing ſo oppoſite and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the rule of reaſon, and that freedome that all men naturally co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, that I ſhall as ſoone renounce the fundamentalls of my faith, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it. But the long continuance of the Monarchicall governement (which indeede is the moſt abſolute of all others, if it do not exceede the ſweet mixtute of legall moderation) the corruption of Princes, and the fawning principles of Court Paraſites; theſe are they which by degrees have inſinuated theſe abſurd and falſe poſitions, and adulterated the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall conſtitution of ſo pure and happie a Dominion. Thus much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt abſolute Monarchy in generall.</p>
            <p>And now after all, let us who are Engliſh Subjects, &amp; live under the golden mean of mixt &amp; qualified Monarchy (the moſt bleſt dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world if not corrupted through the ambition of Princes or the baſe ſeducement of evill Counſellors) bleſſe God for his goodneſſe who hath not only diſpenſed and beſtowed an equall portion of his bounty upon us, but hath alſo made us abſolute proprietors of what we enjoy, ſo that our lives, liberties and eſtates, doe not depend upon, not are ſubiect to the ſole breath or arbitrary will of our Soveraigne. And I ſhall conclude all with a ſmall variation of that old verſe</p>
            <q>
               <p>Non eſt Lex, Regi, ſed Rex, obnoxia, Legi.</p>
               <l>The lawe's not ſubiect to the greateſt King,</l>
               <l>But doth his will into ſubiection bring.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96490:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
